I'm sorry to be the bearer of bad news,
but everyone online telling you that you
need to be using AI is full of shit.
You think that AI is going to take you
ahead
to the next level,
to put you in front of all your
competitors.
But in fact,
it's slowing you right down
and it's making you dumber in real time.
The reason that so many people use AI,
even right now, me using this title, is
people are obsessed with it.
They seem to think
if they don't adapt to AI that
they're going to fall behind.
But let's just get into some of the issues
with it.
Firstly, ideation. Ideation
is the concept of coming up with ideas of
things to
talk about in content. Two issues I have,
the first one of which is the majority of
creators telling you to use AI for
ideation don't use AI for
ideation. They have a team of writers.
When someone puts out three videos a week
at 30 to 45 minutes, and
every single word is read off a
teleprompter, and that person
is worth tens of
millions of dollars, who do you think
is writing all of the words on the
teleprompter? I'll give you a clue.
It's not AI. It's professional writers.
Often,
they work in teams of up to three to eight
people, and they script, and they
curate,
and they plan every single segment of the
video.
The person that you follow
is often just a puppet. How do I know?
Because I'm jealous of these people.
I wish I had a team of writers.
I wish I could just turn up,
turn the teleprompter on,
and just read shit out and
have people gobble it up. But for me,
I just wouldn't be able to sit here
and read
that out and feel proud about it. So
when it comes to ideation,
if you're going to
rely on ChatGPT or Claude
or whatever it is that you're using,
in essence,
it's as if you've hired someone for 25K a
year at a junior level to come up with
all your ideas.
I've got a really good friend of mine
actually, and he hired
someone on maybe 40K a year,
and suddenly all the ideas that he
was putting forward
were the ideas of someone on 40K a year.
You cannot leave the ideation on what you
talk about to AI, because the ideas will
just not be good enough.
But the most dangerous pitfall people fall
into is
thinking that they are. Second,
when scripting your videos,
it's very important
that you script and curate it.
There's something that happens in writing,
which I
can tell you about,
being a "Sunday Times" number one
best-selling author three
times.
You need to get into a flow state with
your writing.
And I've written over 10,000 marketing
emails in my life, and there's something
that happens that some of you can relate
to.
When you start an email marketing
campaign, often it starts really,
really poor,
and then it's about half to two-thirds
into the email that you actually jump and
find something that's quite good to talk
about, and suddenly you're in your flow
state and you're cracking jokes
and you're putting stuff out there.
And then you go back
and you delete the first part of the
video.
You just take it out.
In the scripting process,
some of your best jokes, some of
your best ideas,
some of the best talking points,
they come out of your own mind.
They can't be found in AI.
If you leave AI and ChatGPT or whatever
to script everything for you, it's dry,
it's robotic. Better yet,
it's predictable.
When people are watching your content,
they know that you're just reading a
script,
and they know that you didn't write it.
One of the biggest pitfalls
that I see so many personal brands falling
into is
thinking that their audience are not
that intelligent.
And if you do that
and you think they're not going to notice
that you're reading a
script that was made in ChatGPT,
you're wrong.
And you might think
that the retention on your video
is poor because the algorithm
sent it to the wrong videos,
but the truth is that the people
that it was sent to,
they're just onto you.
Another place this is prevalent
is LinkedIn.
Anywhere you go on LinkedIn,
you post something, you realize
that the majority of
the comments are bot comments.
People seem to think
that being inauthentic and
getting AI to produce a reply comment will
benefit their brand.
It's so easy to spot.
And here's a question for you guys.
How are you at spotting other people using
AI? Pretty good, right?
But yet you think
when you use it within your own business,
no one's going to
notice. Hmm, double standard.
The next thing is the banter
that you have in a
video. If you follow a script, there
is no banter. There is no laugh.
There is no me showing my shaved head to
Declan, sitting there editing and saying,
"You're next." There
was a video I did on creatine on YouTube a
few years ago.
I was trying to think about who would be
right for having a dose bigger than five
grams. And off-the-cuff, I just said,
"And if you're slightly bigger, if you've
ever been to Thailand
and the ladies there have said, 'Oh,
big boy,' then you might
need a bit more than five grams."
And the amount of comments in
that thread that
said, "Oh my God. The big boy comment.
I'm subscribing to your channel off the
back of that." That
was just a random thing
that came off-the-cuff. I was there. I
was in my flow state. I was enjoying it.
That's what you should be doing with your
content.
So many of you are making videos.
You're not even enjoying it.
I'm enjoying this right now,
telling you that you're pretty fucking
retarded
putting so much lenience onto AI to do
everything for you just because you've
seen
a lot of videos talking about the benefits
of AI when all those people are doing is
just trying to promote their own shit.
Because if we think of the funnel,
I've got a four S system.
We go socials, squeeze, sell, scale.
When people want your data,
they need eyeballs. They need views.
They need top-of-funnel traffic.
So if they're going to talk about AI
and get loads of AI traffic from it,
that's
how they move you down the funnel.
And what are they selling you?
They're not selling you AI stuff.
They're often selling high-ticket
programs.
It's just how they get you in the funnel
in the first place.
Another place I've tried
and tested this is using AI for
thumbnails.
We now have image generation where you can
upload 20 photos of yourself, teach the
AI how you look,
and you can put yourself in all kinds of
different places.
I've come to realize
that these have performed, in most cases,
much worse
than original photos.
Any of you out there on YouTube,
one thing that I would say
is if you can just get a picture,
one picture that's legitimately taken,
nothing's
going to beat that.
My Logan Paul video with the Prime bottle,
the creatine gummy videos,
it's all just a single photo.
And sometimes they perform much better
without any text on them.
If you think that you don't need to create
thumbnails because AI will do it for
you, again,
people can see it's AI-generated,
and they just do not perform as well
as you think. And here's the thing, right.
Let's say that AI is a three out of 10,
it's a five out of 10, it's a seven out of
10, it's a nine out of 10,
whatever you think it is.
Whatever you're using,
your competitors can use.
Whatever great ideas you think you're
getting, are the exact same ideas your
competitors are getting.
Whatever prompts you're putting in,
your other competitors
are getting the same prompts.
And that's where people kind of get a bit
excited
with it. AI is a tool, sure.
But the more information you can give it,
the better.
But even then, like I said before,
it's like a 25K a year junior member
of staff.
I don't want to do this maths You do it
for me.
I don't want to do this research;
you do it for me.
Hey,
here's a 10,000-word script I've just
written about.
Have I missed anything?
And then it'll say,
"Have you considered this, this?" You
go,
"That's a good idea." Then you write it
yourself.
I even think that there can be a white
space on social media having the odd
grammar
mistake, because at least
when people see a grammar mistake these
days, they don't
go, "Oh,
you didn't go to school." They go,
"Fuck me, that's refreshing." Not
seeing that double dash hyphen kicking
about everywhere.
Also, think of it this way. There
is a muscle in your brain that needs to be
trained for creativity.
The way I come up with funny ideas for
email marketing
emails is through training that muscle
and that brain.
Did you read my email yesterday, Declan?
You've got to sort that posture out, bro.
Your neck is at a 90-degree angle right
now.
I wrote an email yesterday about wanking
in a pot.
So that muscle will atrophy
if you don't train it enough.
When there's [chuckles] an idea for coming
up for YouTube videos, if you do not
train that muscle, it will atrophy.
And so many of you watching this,
think about this.
People that tear an ACL have to take six
months off. They come back to training.
They're at their most heightened risk to
get injured again because they've just had
six months off. That's why
if you tweak your back
and pull a muscle or tear your
hamstring,
I would say get moving as soon as you can
because the longer you
rest for, the more inclined you
are to get injured again.
What I'm saying there is these skills,
attributes, and abilities to
generate good ideas on the fly will perish
over time if they're not trained.
So AI,
although could be giving you some insights
every now and then,
if you do not train it, use it or lose it,
for any of you fitness people there.
So what's the solution to this?
Do we delete ChatGPT? No.
I love nothing better than rifting a
four-minute voice note to ChatGPT.
I love using AI. I use it every day.
I just don't rely on it for the important
stuff, such as emulation.
Any of you looking for great ideas, rather
than going to AI, go to YouTube,
go to Instagram, go look at the
best-performing things in
that field because there is a tried
and tested
formula there for what
is currently working.
I just don't understand
if you wanted to make a video about fat
loss, or you want
to do a video about how to structure a
will, or you wanted to make a video on how
to avoid corp tax,
you wouldn't go look to what performed the
best.
There's something called the survive ship
bias where, in essence, any given time,
there are loads of people trying different
things.
And if you go to YouTube
and look at things that
are coming up on your home feed,
they're the ones that survived.
Out of all the people,
they're the ones that
perform the best. There
was a story about World War II where
planes were coming back, and people
were looking at where there
were bullet holes
in them. And they were saying, "Oh,
of course,
there's loads of bullet holes in the
wing.
Let's put more armor on the wings."
And William something, I can't remember
his surname, he said, "No,
don't put armor there.
Put armor in the places where the planes
didn't come back." So if there's bullet
holes there and they made it back,
that's not saying we need to put armor
there.
That's telling us the opposite. This
is the survive ship bias.
Because evidently,
where bullet holes hit that weren't there,
they didn't make it
back.
So when looking to copy people pretty much
ethically online,
look at what's already working.
The next thing would be mastery.
So many of you think
that you can jump past the boring part
and go straight
into the cool, sexy part,
and I'm afraid that just doesn't work.
And where AI makes you dumber,
mastery makes you sound smarter.
So for instance, for a PT,
you want to have years of experience
working with people
on the gym floor. For a physio,
you want to spend years of your life in
the clinic.
If you're a racing car driver,
you want to have spent time,
thousands of hours, in
a car with people so you know
when they understeer, when they oversteer,
when they
overbrake, when they underbrake,
when they come in too tight,
all these things.
And if you can reflect a video about your
experiences of mastery, you're
going to resonate with people so much
better because people, again, are much
smarter than you think,
and they can tell
when you know what you're on about.
Experience will always trump AI in
that realm.
So it's really important
that you guys do your hours because I
always say this.
The years that I spent on the gym floor
were some of my worst-paid hours ever, but
the experiences I got from being out there
are exactly what got me to where I am
today.
And the more hours you can learn in-person
mastery, the more that's going to
translate better to
when you come online because people can
see it.
And again,
if we think about what personal brand is,
personal brand is the
information that you need and personality.
Now, too much personality,
you're doing a vlog, and no one cares.
Too much information,
you're just reading out a script from
ChatGPT.
Personal brand is about finding the middle
ground.
If you want to use information
and you want to use AI to get it, cool.
But you must have your own element of
personality to it because that is what's
going to separate you from all your
competitors online. Again,
imagine a spectrum.
Information, personality.
Personal brand sits in the middle.
And AI is going to be the biggest
hindrance to you developing your personal
brand
if you cannot get your personality across.
All of us are made up of something called
idiosyncrasies.
An idiosyncrasy is something that
is unique to us.
Whether it's me, it's very blunt,
swear too much, can come across rude,
sometimes
condescending,
maybe facetious could be a word that's
thrown around, but
ultimately comes from a place of love.
You shouldn't be using AI as much as you
think you should.
And if you do, it won't work well.
There's going to be a link in the
description if
you want to work with me.
But the main reason I'm here is
if you want to survive in
2026,
you must nail this personal brand
spectrum.
In the next five, 10 years,
AI will be nowhere near able to do
what having a good,
strong personal brand can do.
And what a good personal strong brand can
do is get leads to come to you rather
than you going to them, which
is why I put this live stream out online
for you guys
to watch where you can find out absolutely
everything that you need to.
Dare I say, if you watch this,
you may not even need to hire me
and have me as your
business mentor because I give all the
secret tips and trades away exactly in
this
video. So check that out.